Guide to the Kurt Seligmann Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Kurt Seligmann papers
1883-1991
YCAL MSS 827
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
20.93
(40 boxes) + 1 record album storage, 1 broadside
The Kurt Seligmann Papers consist of correspondence, personal papers, photographs, and artwork documenting his personal life and artwork. The papers provide insight into Seligmann's work as a surrealist painter and engraver and his circle of friends, many of whom were artists and writers. Correspondents include Nicolas Calas, Alexander Calder, Pierre Courthion, Enrico Donati, Jean Dubuffet, Charles Duits, Georges Duthuit, George W. Federoff, Fernand Léger, Pierre Mabille, Robert Motherwell, Tarō Okamoto, Amédée Ozenfant, Wolfgang Paalen, Kay Sage, and Yves Tanguy. Correspondence with collectors and gallerists can also be found in the papers. The correspondence sheds light on Seligmann's efforts following his move to the United States to provide support for his friends left in France during World War II. Correspondence and newspaper clippings provide evidence of Seligmann's work to organize exhibitions of surrealist artwork.
Seligmann, Kurt, 1900-1962
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Arlette Seligmann, 1993-1997.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
14 (Record Album Storage): Use of originals is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Kurt Seligmann (1900-1962)
Kurt Seligmann, Swiss-American painter, printmaker, sculptor, stage designer and writer, was born in Basel, Switzerland on July 20, 1900. Seligmann moved to Paris, France, after studying at the Ecole des Beaux-Arts in Geneva (1920) and at the Accademia di Belle Arti in Florence (1927). While in Paris, Seligmann was associated with the Surrealists and Abstraction-Création groups. During this period he also developed "Neo-Concretism" with Japanese artist Taro Okamoto. He exhibited in Basel, Bern, Brussels, Poland and Tokyo.
Seligmann married Arlette Paraf in 1935. Paraf was the granddaughter of Nathan Wildenstein who founded the Wildenstein Gallery.
At the outbreak of the second World War, Kurt and Arlette Seligmann emigrated to the United States, ultimately settling on a farm in Sugar Loaf, New York. In addition to producing artwork, Seligmann taught at the New School and Brooklyn College, and designed costumes and sets for dance performances. He authored two books on magic: The History of Magic (New York, 1948) and R as Magic, Supernaturalism and Religion (New York, 1968), the latter was published posthumously.
Seligmann died at his home in Sugar Loaf, New York on January 2, 1962.
Scope and Contents
The Kurt Seligmann Papers consist of correspondence, personal papers, photographs, and artwork documenting his personal life and artwork. The papers provide insight into Seligmann's work as a surrealist painter and engraver as well as his circle of friends, many of whom were artists and writers. Correspondents include Nicolas Calas, Alexander Calder, Marc Chagall, Pierre Courthion, Enrico Donati, Jean Dubuffet, Charles Duits, Georges Duthuit, Fernand Leger, Pierre Mabille, André-Aimé-René Masson, Robert Motherwell, Taro Okamoto, Amédée Ozenfant, Wolfgang Paalen, Murdock Pemberton, Kay Sage, and Yves Tanguy. The correspondence sheds light on Seligmann's efforts following his move to the United States to provide support for his friends left in France during World War II. Correspondence and newspaper clippings provide evidence of Seligmann's work to organize exhibitions of surrealist artwork.
Arrangement
Organized into five groupings: I. January 1993 Acquisition. II. January 1993 Acquisition. III. February 1993 Acquisition. IV. December 1997 Acquisition. V. December 1997 Acquisition.
Art -- Collectors and collecting -- United States; Art, American -- 20th Century; Artists, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Artists -- Europe -- 20th Century -- Archives; Expatriate artists; Modernism (Art); Surrealism -- France; Surrealist artists; World War, 1939-1945 -- France; World War, 1939-1945 -- Refugees -- France; Negatives (photographic) -- United States -- 20th Century; Drawings (visual works) -- United States -- 20th Century; Etchings (prints) -- United States -- 20th Century; Paintings (visual works) -- United States -- 20th Century; Photographs -- United States -- 20th Century; Photographic prints -- United States -- 20th Century; Scrapbooks; Artists -- United States -- 20th Century; Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; Calas, Nicolas, 1907-1988; Calder, Alexander, 1898-1976; Courthion, Pierre, 1902-; Donati, Enrico, 1909-2008; Dubuffet, Jean, 1901-1985; Duits, Charles, 1925-1991; Duthuit, Georges, 1891-1973; Federoff, George W., 1906-2001; Kuh, Katharine, 1904-1994; Léger, Fernand, 1881-1955; Ludgin, Earle, 1898-1981; Mabille, Pierre, 1904-1952; Motherwell, Robert, 1915-1991; Okamoto, Tarō, 1911-1996; Ozenfant, Amédée, 1886-1966; Paalen, Wolfgang, 1907-1959; Sage, Kay, 1898-1963; Seligmann, Kurt, 1900-1962; Tanguy, Yves, 1900-1955
- January 1993 Acquisition, 1883-1991; 1; 14.84; (26 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Contains correspondence, writings, artwork, personal papers, diaries, photographs, negatives, scrapbooks, notes, notebooks, card files, printed material and a record. Includes sketches by Seligmann as well as reviews of Seligmann's work.
  Arrangement
  Not arranged in any particular order.
  - Littlefield, William. Figure & Ground Relation, 1953 May (Box 1)
  - Seligmann, Kurt. "Narration", undated (Box 1)
  - Lecture notes, undated (Box 1)
  - Seligmann, Kurt. "Le totem de Gedem Skanish", 1939, undated (Box 1)
  - Newspapers and newspaper clippings, 1939-1955; 5 (Box 1)
  - Printed material, 1926-1959, undated; 3 (Box 1)
  - Receipts and notes, 1955-1967, undated (Box 1)
  - Sketchbooks and drawings, undated; 6 (Box 1)
  - Paris, correspondence, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Unsorted correspondence, circa 1947-1961; 2 (Box 1)
    Contains correspondence with publishers, galleries, museums, curators, collectors, and others. Correspondents include: Frans Boers, Walter Grab, Nesto Jacometti, Earle and Mary Ludgin, Amédée Ozenfant, Wolfgang Paalen, Ruth White, and Kurt Wolff.
  - Two-page leaflet printed in black with reproduction of Gauguin's "Le Sourire", undated (Box 1)
  - Referenz zu Scheible's Festkalender, undated (Box 1)
  - Exhibition catalogues and other related material, 1936-1961, undated (Box 1)
  - Receipts, 1937 (Box 2)
  - Empty photograph album, undated (Box 2)
  - Printed material, 1949-1974, undated; 6 (Box 2)
  - Tarnaud, Claude. L'aventure de la Marie-Jeanne, undated (Box 2)
  - Unsorted correspondence, notes, and illustrations, 1938-1965, undated; 2 (Box 2)
    Includes biographical statement. Correspondence consists of both incoming and outgoing letters. Correspondents include galleries (Tone Price, Katharine Kuh) and collectors (L. A. Weinrott, Earle Ludgin).
  - Notebook, undated (Box 2)
  - Financial records, 1931-1939, undated (Box 2)
  - Records relating to purchase of an Indian Totem Pole, 1938-1939, undated (Box 2)
  - Seligmann, Kurt. "Notes sur le Zohar", 1960 July (Box 2)
  - New York University. College of Engineering. Course of Camouflage, 1942 (Box 2)
  - Seligmann, Kurt. Le Miroir de la Magie, slipcase, undated (Box 2)
  - "An Axolotl in Fire," drawing, undated (Box 2)
  - Sketchbooks and drawings, undated; 3 (Box 2)
  - Bibliographic index cards, undated (Box 2)
  - Cardboard file for Seligmann's library, undated (Box 2)
  - Hemispheres, No. 1-4, 6, 1943-1945; 3 (Box 3)
  - Fenn's Character Cards Used By the College of Chinese Studies, Peking, undated (Box 3)
  - Financial records, 1944-1963; 5 (Box 3)
  - Printed material, 1959-1964, undated; 3 (Box 3)
  - Unsorted correspondence and printed ephemera, circa 1956-1959 (Box 3)
    Correspondence is comprised of letters from galleries, museums, and collectors. Includes proof for Gallery Twenty-One "1842 Six Poets."
  - Family correspondence, business, 1937-1955 (Box 3)
  - Business cards and notes, undated (Box 4)
  - Drawings and notes, undated (Box 4)
  - Arts, No. 822, 1961 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence
    - Sugar Loaf, 1952-1955 (Box 4)
    - Villa Seurat, 1955, undated (Box 4)
    - Seligmann publications, 1953, undated (Box 4)
    - Artists' original Christmas cards, invitations, etc., circa 1958-1959 (Box 4)
    - Russell, Alfred and Andrée, 1955-1956, undated (Box 4)
    - White, Ruth, 1956 (Box 4)
    - Unsorted correspondence, circa 1951-1962; 3 (Box 4)
      Contains correspondence with galleries, museums, curators, Jean-Marie d'Amat, Nicolas Calas, George Fedoroff, Ivy Grierson, Earle Ludgin, László Moholy-Nagy, Taro Okamoto, Kay Sage, Kurt Wolff, as well as correspondence concerning Seligmann's summer art course (1951).
  - Receipts, writings, and newspaper clippings, 1940s-1960s; 2 (Box 4)
  - Seligmann, Kurt. "Esthetic Experience", 1950-1954 (Box 4)
    Includes material relating to the Artists Equity Association.
  - Receipts, printed ephemera, 1957-1963, undated (Box 4)
  - Original woodcuts, undated (Box 4)
  - Unsorted writings, undated; 3 (Box 4)
  - Notebooks and notes, undated; 3 (Box 4)
  - Film, 1954-1955, undated (Box 4)
    Includes press releases and material relating to the Creative Film Foundation.
  - Unsorted papers, circa 1930-1963; 2 (Box 4)
  - Exhibition announcements, 1956, undated (Box 4)
  - Unsorted writings, 1958-1959, undated; 4 (Box 5)
    Includes correspondence and writings of others.
  - "Surrealism", undated (Box 5)
  - Material relating to Brooklyn College, 1956-1962, undated; 2 (Box 5)
  - Notebooks, undated; 3 (Box 5)
  - Newspaper clippings and magazines, 1937-1974, undated; 2 (Box 5)
  - Sketchbooks, undated; 4 (Box 5)
  - Seligmann, Kurt. "Vertiges" and "Le Mauvais Oeil", undated (Box 5)
  - Bookseller catalogues, undated (Box 5)
  - Diary notes, undated (Box 5)
  - Exhibition announcements, 1945-1961, undated; 2 (Box 5)
  - Illustrations, photostats, undated; 4 (Box 6)
  - Exhibition catalogues, 1940-1953, undated (Box 6)
  - Bookseller catalogues, notes, and illustrations, 1952-1956, undated (Box 6)
  - Original painting on wood, undated (Box 6)
  - Exhibition announcements and notebook, undated (Box 6)
  - Ballet manuscripts, undated (Box 6)
  - Appointment calendar, 1961 (Box 6)
  - Notebook, undated (Box 6)
  - Bibliographic index cards, A-Z, undated; 5 (Box 6)
  - Diary notes, 1936 (Box 6)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1930s (Box 6)
  - Sketchbooks, undated; 2 (Box 6)
  - "The Middle Ages", undated (Box 7)
  - Sketchbooks, undated; 4 (Box 7)
  - Notebooks, 1935, undated; 3 (Box 7)
  - Address book, undated (Box 7)
  - Desk calendar, 1914-1961; 7 (Box 7)
  - Etched metal plate, undated (Box 7)
  - Sketchbooks, undated; 3 (Box 7)
  - Sketchbooks and drawings, undated; 9 (Box 8)
  - Unsorted writings, undated; 4 (Box 8)
  - Diary notes, undated; 2 (Box 8)
  - Unsorted printed ephemera, 1954-1967, undated (Box 8)
  - Unsorted correspondence, 1940s-1950s; 5 (Box 8)
    Contains correspondence with galleries, museums, as well as Brooklyn College, Nicolas Calas, Alexander Calder, Charles Duits, Peggy and Howard Gibbs, Jean Hélion, Earle and Mary Ludgin, Claude Nerguy, Taro Okamoto, Édouard Roditi, Walter Skolnik, Yomiuri Shimbun (relating to the Japan Independent Art Exhibition), Kurt Wolff, and outgoing correspondence. Also includes printed ephemera.
  - D'Arcy Galleries, financial records, 1962, undated (Box 8)
  - Inventory and appraisal of Kurt Seligmann's books, 1962 (Box 9)
  - Drawings, undated (Box 9)
  - Unsorted writings, undated; 2 (Box 9)
  - Original etchings, undated (Box 9)
  - Arlette Seligmann's tax returns, 1988 (Box 9)
  - Bericht der Gottfried-Keller Stiftung, circa 1980 (Box 9)
  - Notes relating to K. S. Bosch, undated (Box 9)
  - Seligmann, Kurt. "The Birth of a Painting", undated (Box 9)
  - Illustrations, printed material, undated; 2 (Box 9)
  - Exhibition catalogues, 1954-1970 (Box 9)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1950-1956, undated (Box 9)
  - Japanese exhibition, 1956 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence
    - Business correspondence, 1953-1954 (Box 9)
    - Exhibitions, 1954-1956, undated (Box 9)
    - Earle Ludgin & Company, 1956, undated (Box 9)
    - Meyer, Henri, 1945-1957, undated (Box 9)
    - Charlet, Blanche, 1955, undated (Box 9)
    - Unsorted correspondence, 1946-1956, undated; 8 (Box 9)
      Contains correspondence with Michèle Babou, André Breton, Gelett Burgess, Michel Cadoret, Nicolas Calas, George Fedoroff, Max Granick, George Grosz, Emil and Cécile Guggenheim, Marguerite Hagenbach, Albert Heider, Ralph Hyams, Martin James, Marcel Jean, John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation, Earle and Mary Ludgin, Edith Lutyens, and outgoing correspondence. Also includes photographs, printed ephemera, and bank statements (1952).
    - "A" General, 1949-1954, undated (Box 9)
    - "B" General, 1950-1953, undated (Box 9)
    - "C" General, 1949-1952, undated (Box 9)
    - "D" General, 1950-1961, undated (Box 9)
    - "E" General, 1950-1951, undated (Box 9)
    - "H" General, 1949-1953, undated (Box 9)
    - "I" General, 1952-1953 (Box 9)
    - "K" General, 1949-1953, undated (Box 10)
    - "L" General, 1949-1953, undated (Box 10)
    - "P" General, 1950-1953, undated (Box 10)
    - "S" General, 1949-1959, undated (Box 10)
    - Unsorted correspondence, 1950s-1960s; 3 (Box 10)
      Contains correspondence from Martin James, Hilda Jarman, correspondence regarding finances and French taxes, and outgoing correspondence.
    - Family correspondence, 1940s-1950s; 2 (Box 10)
  - Exhibition catalogues, newspaper clippings, circa 1948-1960; 3 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence and printed ephemera, 1946-1962, undated (Box 10)
  - Exposition Internationale du Surréalisme, 1938; 9 (Box 10)
    Includes clippings, invitations and other ephemera.
  - Film negatives, undated; 6 (Box 10)
  - Photographic slides, undated (Box 10)
  - Printed material, 1940s (Box 10)
  - Childhood photographs, 1919-1933, undated (Box 10)
  - Seligmann, Kurt. "Hieronymus Bosch, Painter of Mysteries", undated (Box 10)
  - Illustrations, photostats, undated (Box 10)
  - Exhibition catalogues, announcements, and invitations, 1948-1955, undated; 4 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence
    - Duits, Charles, 1947, undated (Box 11)
    - The New School, 1951-1953, undated (Box 11)
    - Unsorted correspondence, "To be filed, unimportant miscellany", 1941-1959 (Box 11)
    - Unsorted correspondence: includes correspondence with George Fedoroff, Marguerite and Henri Meyer, Kay Sage, and outgoing correspondence, 1947, undated (Box 11)
    - Unsorted correspondence: includes correspondence with Arthur Naitove, form letters, and outgoing correspondence (Box 11)
    - Unsorted correspondence: includes correspondence with Sabine Gova, Eva Gudeman, photographs, and outgoing correspondence, 1941-1943 (Box 11)
    - Unsorted correspondence: includes correspondence with George Fedoroff, Emil and Cécile Guggenheim, outgoing correspondence, financial papers, a portrait photograph of a young girl, and printed ephemera, 1941 (Box 11)
    - Unsorted correspondence: includes correspondence with Brooklyn College, 1944-1959 (Box 11)
    - Unsorted correspondence: includes correspondence regarding entry permits to Mexico, 1939-1943 (Box 11)
    - Unsorted correspondence: includes correspondence with Creative Film Foundation, Blanche Charlet, Emil and Cécile Guggenheim, Lucille Paris, Henri Pastoreau,and Ned Rorem, 1947-1951 (Box 11)
    - Unsorted correspondence: includes correspondence with Jean Paul Collet, László Moholy-Nagy, Dr. L.R. Sanguineti, as well as cartoons, 1942-1957 (Box 11)
    - Unsorted correspondence: includes correspondence with American Federation of Arts, The Art Institute of Chicago, George Federoff, Ivan Goll, Leo Kok, Katharine Kuh, Alberto Magnelli, Museum of Modern Art (New York), Benjamin Péret, Gotthard Schuh, R. Th. Stoll, and Georges Wildenstein, 1947-1959 (Box 11)
    - Unsorted correspondence: includes correspondence with Michel Cadoret, National War Poster Competition, and correspondence regarding the estate of Helene Guggenheim Seligmann, 1941-1961 (Box 11)
    - Unsorted correspondence: includes correspondence with Barbara Reis, Ruth White Gallery, Society of Illustrators, and Allen S. Weller (University of Illinois), 1949-1957 (Box 11)
    - Unsorted correspondence: includes correspondence with Edgard Varèse and Montgomery Ward, 1949-1953 (Box 11)
    - Unsorted correspondence: includes correspondence with the Hudson Shipping Company, Department of State (Visa Division), and doctors, 1942-1943 (Box 11)
    - Unsorted correspondence: includes correspondence with Dorothy O'Brien and Taro Okamoto, 1951-1952 (Box 11)
    - Unsorted correspondence: includes correspondence with The Art Institute of Chicago, Carl Schniewind, Walter Sorell, Leize Duncan Stewart, and The Tiger's Eye, 1951-1953 (Box 11)
    - Unsorted correspondence: includes correspondence with Brooklyn College, George Fedoroff, University of Minnesota, Momentum, and Albert Meyer, 1950-1960 (Box 11)
    - Unsorted correspondence: includes correspondence with Durlacher Brothers, The Print Club, László Moholy-Nagy, and printed ephemera, 1939-1952 (Box 11)
  - Metze, Austin. Poems, 1991 December (Box 12)
  - Kurt Seligmann's curriculum vitae, undated (Box 12)
  - Receipts and notes (Box 12)
  - Unsorted writings, undated (Box 12)
    Includes typescripts of Yvan Goll's "Jean Sans Terre Aborde Au Dernier Port," "Jean Sans Terre a Manhattan," "Jean Sans Terre Nettoyer par le Vide," and English translations.
  - Material relating to Brooklyn College, 1937-1959, undated; 2 (Box 12)
    Includes correspondence.
  - Items removed from books in Kurt Seligmann's library, 1889-1964, undated; 13 (Box 12)
  - Printed material, 1906-1932, undated; 14 (Box 13)
  - "Culture Ace - Seligmann - Bouchard Interview", 1950 May 5; 1 78rpm record (Box 14 (Record Album Storage))
    Conditions Governing Access
    Use of originals is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - Photograph album, undated; 7 (Box 15)
  - Photograph album, undated; 5 (Box 16)
  - Photograph album, undated; 3 (Box 17)
  - Empty envelopes, undated (Box 17)
  - Untitled illustration, undated (Box 17)
  - Notes, undated; 3 (Box 17)
  - Printed material, 1883-1942, undated; 4 (Box 18)
  - Sketchbooks, undated; 4 (Box 18)
  - Photograph of unidentified man, undated (Box 19)
  - Film negatives, undated (Box 19)
  - Original etchings, undated; 2 (Box 19)
  - Original artwork by S. Charcoune, undated (Box 19)
  - Drawings, 1958, undated; 2 (Box 19)
  - Société des Americanistes diploma awarded to Kurt Seligmann, 1939 February 7 (Box 19)
  - Illustrations, undated (Box 19)
  - Scrapbook, 1960s (Box 20)
  - Scrapbook, 1940s (Box 21)
  - Scrapbook, 1940s (Box 22)
  - Scrapbook, 1930s (Box 23)
  - Scrapbooks, undated; 3 (Box 24)
  - Scrapbooks, 1940s; 2 (Box 25)
  - Scrapbooks, 1932, undated (Box 26 (Oversize))
- January 1993 Acquisition, 1934-1962; 2; 0.21; (1 box)
  Contains printed material, including clippings and magazines.
  - Items removed from books of Kurt Seligmann's library, 1946-1943, undated; 2 (Box 27)
  - Critique, 1946 July (Box 27)
  - Lettres, 1946 (Box 27)
  - Linien, 1934-1935 (Box 27)
  - Les Cahiers Astrologiques, 1962 March-April (Box 27)
  - Cue, 1941 May 3 (Box 27)
  - Town & Country, 1947-1948 (Box 27)
- February 1993 Acquisition, 1946; 3; 0.21; (1 box)
  Contains typescript of Wolfgang Paalen's play "The Beam of the Balance."
  - Paalen, Wolfgang, "The Beam of the Balance," typescript, 1946 (Box 28)
- December 1997 Acquisition, 1930-1980; 4; 2.42; (3 boxes)
  Contains correspondence, writings, notes, photographs, financial and legal papers and printed material by or relating to Kurt Seligmann. Includes letters from André Breton, Robert Motherwell, Charles Henri Ford, Julian Levy and others. Lecture notes and photographs of art and costumes by Kurt Seligmann can also be found in the acquisition.
  Arranged into two series: I. Subject Files and Other Papers, 1930-1980. II. Correspondence, 1937-1959.
  - Subject Files and Other Papers, 1930-1980
    - Seligmann - published articles and art work, 1950, undated (Box 29)
    - Seligmann publications, pertinent correspondence, 1941-1945 (Box 29)
    - Correspondence pertaining to Magic Book, comments, etc., undated (Box 29)
    - The Mirror of Magic, related correspondence, 1958-1959 (Box 29)
    - Inventory of books and prints at Cornell, 1940, 1980 (Box 29)
    - Art Supplies, 1952-1953 (Box 29)
    - Ballet. Photographs and Designs
      - Seligmann Designs for dance costumes, undated (Box 29)
      - Dance costume photos, undated (Box 29)
      - Ballet designs, 1941-1957 (Box 29)
    - Bibliography and vitae, 1956, undated (Box 29)
    - Exhibition catalogue, 1935 (Box 29)
    - Catalogue of gallery exhibitions, 1943-1955 (Box 29)
    - Exhibitions: Nierendorf, 1941 (Box 29)
    - Exhibition announcements, 1939 (Box 29)
    - Financial records, 1941-1943 (Box 29)
    - Immigration
      - Visa information, 1941-1944 (Box 29)
      - Refugee problems, 1940-1941 (Box 29)
    - Lecture notes, undated (Box 29)
    - Location of works, 1945; undated (Box 29)
    - Seligmann material that was possibly inspiration, undated (Box 29)
    - Notebook, undated (Box 29)
    - Paintings to 1939, 1930-1939 (Box 29)
    - Paintings 1940-50, 1940-1950 (Box 29)
    - Photographs of drawings, undated (Box 29)
    - Teaching: New School, Briarcliff, Brooklyn College, 1941-1944, undated (Box 29)
    - Villa Seurat, 1950-1959; 2 (Box 29)
    - Writings: Doctor Faustus, 1972, undated (Box 29)
    - Drawing, undated (Box 29)
  - Correspondence, 1937-1959
    - Family letters, 1950-1957 (Box 29)
    - Unsorted correspondence: includes correspondence with Georges Duthuit, Ivy Grierson, Peggy Guggenheim, Ernest Hediger, Fernand Léger, Museum of Modern Art (New York), Henri Peyre, J.W. Poe, and Yves Tanguy, 1941-1951 (Box 29)
    - Unsorted correspondence: includes correspondence with Jacques Dupin and photostats of correspondence with Jacques Goldschmidt, 1952-1953 (Box 29)
    - Unsorted correspondence: includes correspondence with George Amberg, Center Art Council, Minneapolis School of Art, University of Minnesota (regarding UNICORN project), Walker Art Center, and ephemera, 1958 (Box 29)
    - Unsorted correspondence concerning "livres anciens, offres, notes", 1942-1957 (Box 29)
    - Unsorted correspondence: contains correspondence concerning International Exhibition of Modern Art in Japan, correspondents include Asahi-Shimbun Press and Civic Program Department, Gendai Geijyutsu, Taro Okamoto, T. Toyama, insurers, and correspondence regarding damage to Kay Sage and Hedda Sterne paintings, 1955-1958 (Box 29)
    - Unsorted correspondence: contains correspondence with Ivan Goll, Carl Holty, Harriet Janis, Katharine Kuh, Earle Ludgin, Reba Paeff Mirsky, Alice Neiland, Press of James A. Decker, Tone Price, M. Garreau-Dombasle, Carl Schniewind, typescript for "Forum on The Young Artist and Society -- Constant Aesthetic Values," and list of addresses, 1939-1954 (Box 29)
    - Unsorted correspondence: includes correspondence with Metropolitan Museum of Art, Mrs. Amédée Ozenfont, Henri Pastoureau, Philip Lamantia, and typescripts, circa 1940-1958 (Box 30)
    - Family correspondence, 1940 (Box 30)
    - Unsorted correspondence: includes correspondence with Robert Amadou, Deutsche Verlag-Anstalt GmbH, Kurt Wolff (Pantheon Books), and ephemera relating to the Arosa Sky passenger ship, and curriculum vitae for Pierre Courthion, 1957-1959 (Box 30)
    - Unsorted correspondence: includes correspondence with American Federation of Arts, Ruth Horton, Katharine Kuh, Mary Ludgin, and Kurt Wolff, 1955-1958 (Box 30)